Hello, welcome back to the
Wheel of Life home retreat,
where this horse race
is coming to an end.
We've reached
session 24 of 25,
and this session is called
"My Hair on Fire,"
and the picture you see here is of a guy
whose clothes and hair are both on fire.
Let's go to the Tibetan and we can see
why we use this image.
DES NA BSHES SPRING LAS
BSHES SPRING refers to
a famous book
by Arya Nagarjuna,
it is called "The Letter to the King".  I'm
sorry, "Letter to a Friend".
His friend was King Udayibhadra.
And he sent this letter to the king.
I think it's interesting
that Pabongka Rinpoche quotes it
so frequently in his lam rim,
because I was fortunate enough
to work a lot on that text
when I was very young.
My friend Art Engle,
a fellow student,
a dear fellow student,
and my teacher translated that book.
And what I realized
while studying that book
is that it's a lam rim, okay?
So we tend to think
that the lam rim,
the teachings of the steps of the path,
began in Tibet,
but that is not true.
This book in Sanskrit
is called Suhrleka.
Written by Nagarjuna
almost 2,000 years ago, it
is a kind of
very beautiful lam rim.
And Pabongka Rinpoche
quotes two famous verses here.
MGO'AM GOS LA GLO BUR ME SHOR NA
Suppose your clothes
or hair suddenly catch on fire.
And by the way, this happened with someone
during my three-year retirement.
Someone got too close to
the fire
and...
their clothes caught fire,
and that's very, very dangerous.
So you have to...
We were taught in the Boy Scouts
that you have to knock them down
immediately,
push them down,
and then roll them away.
So that's what I did.
DE DAG PHYIR BZLOG BGYI BA
BTANG NAS KYANG
If your clothes or hair catch fire, you
won't do other things.
You will immediately do everything you can
to stop the fire.  You're
not going to say, "Oh, my hair
is on fire,
but I think I'll
finish my coffee first."
We have a job like that.
YANG SRID MED PAR BGYI
We want to extinguish the fire
of rebirth.
We have very little time
in this life.
As long as you are healthy,
as long as you can still meditate,
as long as your mind
is still clear,
as long as you still have food
and a place to stay, you do
n't have time to do
many other things.
This fire is burning you now.
Then you have to stop everything else
and try to put out this fire.
DI LAS CHES MCHOG DGOS PA
GZHAN MA MCHIS There is
nothing more important
that you have to do in your life.
And...
in general, I've followed this
in my life.
And the fact is, if you want to put out
that fire, you
won't have time to do
many other things.
So you may have to give up
many things that other people do in their lives.
And I've been doing that
for almost 50 years,
and I can report, I can tell you, I
believe I made the right decision.
So, for example,
I'm really bad at buying
birthday presents
for my family.
And it's not that I don't love them.
We love each other very much.
But if I dedicate the time
to going to the store
to choose a gift
for each member of the family—
we are a large family—
then I won't have time
to do those three things:
Vipashyana,
trying to understand
dependence and emptiness;
shamatha,
do my meditation practice
every day, without breaking it
to go to the store
to buy birthday presents.
And then there is the daily study
and practice of morality,
which I need to support
my meditation.
Then Nagarjuna says here...
Nagarjuna says here:
"It's as if your hair
is on fire. There
is nothing more important
at this moment."
Put out that fire
and then do other things.
Become a Buddha
and then buy birthday presents.
TSUL KHRIMS DAG DANG
How are you going to put out this fire?
SHES RAB BSAM GTAN GYIS
You must use TSUL KHRIMS,
which means
treating other people gently,
with kindness, without harming other people;
SHES RAB, that wisdom
which understands emptiness,
vipashyana being the highest form;
and then shamatha, a good
and stable state of meditation.
If you remember, these are the three parts
of the woodcutter. A
sharp axe, which is wisdom;
good focus like that still flame,
to strike in the right place;
and then two strong arms of morality
to wield the axe.
Then, if you use those three,
you will reach MYA NGAN 'DAS.
The text says MYA NGAN 'DAS, Nirvana.
Also called ZHI BA,
which means peace.
Also called DUL BA,
which means that you have
complete control over yourself.  same.
Also called
DRI MED PA'I GO 'PHANG,
the state beyond
all impurities.
Also called MI RGA, you
no longer have to grow old.
MI 'CHI means you
no longer have to die.
ZAD MI 'TSAL means:
This life and this purity will
never end.
In "Letter to a Friend,"
the last line is strange.
SA CHU ME RLUNG NYI ZLA
BRAL THOB MDZOD
You should try to reach
that place
where you have no earth,
water, fire, and wind,
and by the way, also...
get rid of the sun
and the moon.
Now... that last line...
I thought we should take a little detour
on the journey, which I like to do.
What does that last line mean?
The other words for Nirvana
are easy.
Peace means, of course,
"I no longer have negative emotions;
it is peaceful."
DUL BA means, "I have self-control."
Of course.
DRI MA MED PA, no more problems in my body,
no more problems in my mind; I do
n't have to grow old, I don't have to
die,
my pure life continues
forever.
That's it.  Easy.
But what does
SA CHU ME RLUNG NYI ZLA BRAL mean?
What does it mean to conquer earth,
water, fire, wind...
sun and moon? I
went to find some commentaries.
The one I enjoyed the most
was by a great Mongolian author, his name is
Chuje Ngawang Pelden.
Chuje means Lord of Dharma.
He lived about...
I think 200 years ago.
And...
Here is his commentary
on that last line.
So we go deeper,
and that's what we do,
and that's why
this teaching
of Lam Rim is so slow.
SA CHU ME RLUNG NYI ZLA
BRAL THOB MDZOD.
He says, "What
about this strange last line?"
So, there's a Mongolian master.
He says, "What about
this strange last line?"
He says: SA CHU MED RLUNGS.
These four elements.
That's easy.
DI LA BYED means:
It refers to the four elements.
And it means that after you
reach Nirvana
or become a Buddha, you
don't have this normal body
made of these four elements.
You have  What we call a
rainbow body.
Why is it called a
rainbow body?
From a distance,
a rainbow appears to have a shape
and colors,
but when you get close
to the rainbow,
you can pass your hand through it,
and the physical body of a Buddha
is similar.
Now here's the part I like
about his commentary; it's very sweet.
He says: NYI ZLA. Why does he mention
the sun and the moon?
KHYAD PAR 'PHAGS BSTOD LAS.
This is called...
This is a famous book called
"Praise of the One
Who Is Exaltedly Superior."
It's a poem.
No. He's going to quote, he's going
to quote a book.
It's a famous eulogy.
Eulogy means a poem of praise,
which is found in the Tengyur.
And he says:
NE TZOS NYI MA BRNGOL NAS NO,
which
is probably a mistake...
here everything is misspelled
and misspelled.
So I had to replace
a lot of words, okay?
But he says:
THAR PA MCHIS PAR BSHAD
CES GRAGS.
The  Parrot, the green parrot...
that talking bird
pecked the sun
with its beak
and then they say it reached
Nirvana.
What's all that about? This is
supposed to explain
the sun and the moon. There is
no sun anymore, there is no
moon anymore.
Forget the sun and the moon.
DRANG SRONG means
a Hindu saint, his
name is RGYAS PA'I BU,
with some miraculous powers,
took a parrot or became
a parrot. It's not clear.
He flew to the sun,
pecked it, and made a hole in
the sun,
and then that saint
went into the hole
and reached Nirvana.
Then this Mongolian master,
who is a great, great master,
says that Shantideva...
Oh, sorry, the book by Nagarjuna,
they are criticizing this idea
that Nirvana is a place
on the other side of the moon or something like that.
Then he criticizes...
He says sun and... when the book says,
"You are free from the sun and the moon," it
means you are free
from this silly idea
about what Nirvana is.
I found another interesting one...
Yes, here's a
Rendawa's comment.
Rendawa was a Sakya master
who was Tsongkhapa's teacher.
And when he explains the sun
and the moon,
PHYI ROLA PA KHA CIG.
Some non-Buddhists say
YANG PHYI ROL PA KHA CIG.
It is at the end of his quote.
KHA BA DUNG RGYA SPOS BA
ZHO BA MO MU TIG MDOG.
He says: "Some people think
that when you reach Nirvana
you enter a white light.
"It's like the color of snow,
" or the color of a white seashell,
"or like the color of a pearl
or the color of yogurt.
And it feels like an umbrella is
covering you."
And these are all strange ideas
about Nirvana.
So he says,
when this book says,
"You go beyond the sun
and the moon," it
means you go beyond
these silly ideas about,
"Oh, Nirvana is like a big white umbrella
and you stay under the umbrella
like in a sun donut."
Sun donut, with a hole
in the middle.
And you may say
that those are just stupid old ideas
from some weird groups
in India,
but you could examine what ideas
you have about what Nirvana is.
And perhaps it's not so different from
the white umbrella.
Now, just for fun,
something I enjoy doing,
I thought you might like to go
to a...
This is a book by
Pabangka Rinpoche himself.
And this is a beautiful kind
of book genre,
it's a type of literature.
And his name is DRIS LAN.  DRIS LAN
stands for questions and answers.
So, even in this course,
we're going to do a special masterclass
and I'll take your questions
and answer them live.
In addition, in the extended course,
they will be able to ask questions directly
online or in person,
or via the internet to ACI senior teachers
.
But in ancient times,
someone would sit there
carving the question.
So here is a question that someone
actually asked Pabongka Rinpoche
probably about 100 years ago.
BSHES SPRING LAS, SA CHU ME RLUNG
NYI ZLA BRAL THOB MDZOD
So what about the last line
of "Letter to a Friend"
that talks about: "You reached Nirvana
where you no longer have sun or moon"?
Ah, and here is
Pabongka's own answer,
because he didn't answer it, he did
n't ask the question in his lam rim,
but someone asked him later:
"What was that line?"
And by the way,
this is the great benefit
of us having
5 million pages
of digitized deeds
from the last 33 years.
And I know many of you
watching this lam rim are helping
to organize the fundraising
for that digitization.
I wanted to thank you for that.
And the reason I can go into more detail
with you
is because of your fundraising.
And it definitely helps the poor people
around the world whom we train.
For 33 years.
And it's beautiful now, some of those ladies I
met
in the first year of this project
had children,
and now those children are working
alongside them on the computer.
Okay, so here it says:
PHYI ROL PA 'GA' ZHIG GIS
'BYUNG BA BZHI DANG NYI ZLA SOGS LA
THOB BYA MTHAR THUG TU' DZIN PA DANG.
It says: "Some people...
"strange old schools,
" "they think Nirvana
is like a white light
" where you go and stay
in this white light.
THAR PA GZUGS CAN DU 'DOD PA.
These are strange ideas
that Nirvana is a physical place.
But if you really want to go to the
real Nirvana,
you need those three trainings:
morality,
concentration,
and wisdom.
Yes, I have to say
that a lot of people think
that if you study this section
that we've covered with 25 classes,
if you study it well,
then you will reach Nirvana.
And you know,
people think it's...
like you're
really drunk.
And you're like that...
for the rest of the time
and you're like in another space.
This is not Nirvana at all.
The definition of Nirvana:
NYON SGRIB MA LUS PAR
SPANGS PA'I SO SOR BRTAG 'GOG
Basically, you get rid
of your anger, jealousy,
and other negative emotions
forever.
That's nirvana.
So Xiaoping, for example,
was translating for me here yesterday,
and she's translating for me here today,
in the same place.
So it's possible that
she reached nirvana last night,
and she wouldn't look any different.
Okay? So you have to understand that.
The person sitting next to you
might have reached nirvana last night
because of these great classes.
And they won't change; their
outward appearance won't change. They
no longer have negative emotions,
and you can't make them angry.
Okay, let's go back to lam rim.
But that kind of deepening
is only possible
because we have a database
that we built over 33 years. I
reckon we still have 117 years to go,
so I hope you'll continue to help,
and I thank you for your help so far.
Especially the friends
from the Gold Club.
CES GSUNGS PA LTAR, SKYES BU 'TRAE
GI NYAMS  SU BLANG BYA NI
Well, what is it that...
people with this average motivation,
what are they trying to achieve?
They just want to stop suffering
forever for themselves.
Well, what
should they focus on?
LHAG PA'I BSLAB PA GSUM
Those three extraordinary trainings:
always being kind
to other people,
doing your meditation
every morning,
and studying, studying,
studying about emptiness.
Now,
GSUM YIN PAS SKYES BU CHEN PO'I
CHOS SKOR MI 'KHRID NA
SKABS' DIR BSLAB PA GSUM
KA 'CHAD DGOS
Now, if I weren't going to teach
you
the highest path, the
Mahayana path,
if this were just a series
of lectures
on how to attain Nirvana,
not Buddhahood...
Of course, Buddhahood
means
that your whole body changes,
your mind changes,
you can help people
on billions of planets at the same time.
Nirvana just means,
"I, a person here on this couch,
feel no anger, no jealousy."
That by  True, that means you've stepped off
the Wheel of Life.
But not everyone who attains Nirvana
attains Buddhahood.
Buddhahood, your whole being changes.
And you are able to help
countless beings
on countless planets
at the same time.
Then Pabongka Rinpoche says,
"I'm not finished with you
after you finish this Nirvana thing."
"I have a great plan for you.
We're going to go to the teachings
of the greater path,
the Mahayana teachings,
where you learn to become
a Buddha."
"To reach that Buddhahood
you will also need
"these same three trainings.
"So, if I weren't going to teach you
this higher path,
if I were only teaching you
about Nirvana,
well, I would teach you the details
of those three trainings today.
But, I am going to teach you
those higher goals,
so I think we'll save
two of those trainings for later.
Like shamatha training,
deep meditation."
"Vipashyana training, a
special vision of emptiness. I
will teach them to you later."
And by the way,
that's my plan too.
After we finish
this book, because...
Pabongka Rinpoche doesn't spend much time
on shamatha and vipashyana in this book,
a little, but not much.
At the end of this book we will go to:
The Great Book on the Steps of the Path.
Lam Rim Chenmo.
That will take us 13 more years
to finish.
We will only do the
shamatha and vipashyana parts.
That part alone
will take 13 years.
Okay?  So...
So I'm telling you, and Pabongka
is telling you,
"We'll get there later, we'll cover those two training sessions
later."
So I'm going to...
TSUL KHRIMS KYI BSLAB PA
RTZAL DU BTON means:
"Let's focus
on an ethical way of life."
That's the PHYAG BZHES here.
PHYAG BZHES means: "That is the tradition
of the high lamas at this time."  We are
only focusing on morality because we will teach you
shamatha and vipashyana later.
Then he quotes again
Letter to a Friend of Nagarjuna.
KHRIMS NI RGYU DANG MI RGYU'I
SA BZHIN DU YON TAN
KUN GYI GZHI RTEN LAGS PAR GSUNGS,
How can I describe the practice
of leading an ethical life?
Think about this planet Earth.
The great earth, the enormous, enormous, enormous,
all the countries resting on this planet.
RGYU DANG MI RGYU'I SA
is an old, old joke.
The earth of this planet
supports everything that moves
and everything that does not move.
So now
we're in Sedona, Arizona.  I do
n't know if you can see,
but these red mountains in the background
are very, very famous.
Six million people
visit us every year.
And the earth, patiently and silently,
holds those mountains all day and all night.
And if you look out the window
you'll see some cars moving.
And the earth also patiently sustains them
day and night.
So whether things
move like cars,
or don't move
like red mountains,
the earth is very patient
and just holds them up.
And Nagarjuna says:
"Your morality is like this."
Okay, you want to meditate,
you want to have direct perception
of emptiness...
By the way, meditation
is like mountains,
and seeing emptiness directly
is like cars.
But someone patient and calm
always has to be there underneath.
The base.
And that is morality.
ZHES PA LTAR YON TAN
THAMS CAD KYI GZHI YIN PAS
Being kind to other people
is the basis of every good quality.
TSUL KHRIMS RNAM PAR DAG PA GAL CHE
Therefore,
never hurting any other person
is extremely important.
'DI NI SANGS RGYAS KYI
BSTAN PA'I RTZA BA
Treating people well
is the root of all Buddhism.
BSRUNG NA PHAN YON CHE
If you maintain an
ethical way of life,
if you are kind to other people,
the benefits that come to you are incredible.
MA BSRUNGS NA NYES
DMIGS KYANG SHIN TU CHE STE
And if you don't...
maintain an ethical lifestyle
and hurt others, you ca
n't imagine the kind of problems you
're creating for yourself.
And I'll tell you another...
important thing that
Buddha said about...
being kind to other people.
If people
in any city or country
are upholding their commitment
to be kind to others,
then Buddha said,
"Buddhism is there."
And if they are not maintaining that kind of commitment
to being kind to other people,
then you can't say
that Buddhism has reached that point.
Then repeat:
DGE SLONG 'DUL BA' DZIN PA
BSTAN PA YOD LA
If there is a person in a city
maintaining
a way of life where he never
harms other people,
then Buddhism exists
in that city.
So, even if there is...
tantra, high secret teachings
reach that city
and everyone is ringing their bells,
but if they are not being kind
to other people,
then we can say
that Buddhist teachings
did not reach that place.
Even though people there practice the
highest teachings, they are not moral.
Therefore,
the Buddha himself said:
NGA NI MYA NGAN 'DAS GYUR NA,
'DI NI KHYOD KYI STON PA ZHES
After I disappear
from this world,
after I reach
my final Nirvana,
part of me will remain
in this world,
and that part of me
will be your teacher forever.
And that's keeping your vows
and not hurting other people.
So, if a person in this world
is keeping their commitment
to never harm other people,
then Buddha said,
"You can say that I am still here."
Final prayer
of this
series.
And then, the twenty-fifth session
will be a review.
RANG RGYUD...
So listen
and let it be like a mantra for you.
Listen to the words.
It's a blessing.
RANG RGYUD KYI TSUL KHRIMS
LA STON PA'I SKU TSAB YIN SNYAM DU
GCES SPRAS BYAS NAS BSRUNG DGOS
Most of you
listening
have probably taken
some kind of Buddhist vows,
at least the ten good deeds:
Do not kill;  do
not steal;
not to harm other people's relationships,
etc.
We can say that in your stream of consciousness
you are maintaining
this lifestyle
where you are kind
to other people.
Then Pabongka says,
"So we can say,
well, you don't have to be perfect,
but those of you who are trying
to keep your book six times over,
and since you heard about this teaching
about the seeds,
you are trying to be kinder
to other people.
As long as you are generally, imperfectly,
trying to be kind to other people,
not perfectly,
we can say that the Buddha
is alive within you.
And GCES SPRAS means,
'Take good care of that Buddha.'
It is the most precious thing in your life.
That is the end of session 24.
In session 25, we will do a review
of all 25 sessions. See you soon
.
I know, Xiaoping, that you are very tired
and have been working very hard, and thank you for translating.
Yay! You
didn't translate 'yay.'
(Xiaoping)
Oh, yay!"